Hello. In this video we're going to talk about something that I've referred to as the economy
你好。在这段视频中，我们将谈论一些我称之为经济的东西
of programming languages.
编程语言。
So the idea behind this video is that before we get into the
所以这段视频背后的想法是，在我们进入
details of how languages are implemented or designed, I wanted to say something about
关于语言是如何实现或设计的详细信息，我想说一些关于
how languages work in the real world and why certain languages are used and others are not.
语言在现实世界中是如何工作的，以及为什么某些语言被使用而另一些语言不被使用。
And if you look around, there's actually a few obvious questions that come up to anybody
如果你环顾四周，实际上有几个明显的问题会出现在任何人面前
who thinks about programming languages for more than a few minutes. One question is,
他思考编程语言的时间超过了几分钟。一个问题是，
why are there so many of these things? We have hundreds, if not thousands, of programming
为什么会有这么多这样的东西？我们有成百上千个节目，如果不是几千个的话。
languages in everyday use, and why do all these things need to exist? Why wouldn't one
日常使用的语言，为什么所有这些东西都需要存在？为什么不是呢？
programming language for example be enough?
比如编程语言就够了吗？
A related question but slightly different is why are there new programming languages?
一个相关但略有不同的问题是，为什么会有新的编程语言？
That given that we have so many programming languages already, what is the need for new
既然我们已经有了这么多编程语言，还需要什么新的
ones to be created? And finally, how do we know a good programming language when we see
有没有要创建的？最后，当我们看到一种好的编程语言时，我们如何知道它是一种好的编程语言呢
it? So what makes a good programming language and what makes a bad programming language?
它?那么，是什么造就了一种好的编程语言，是什么造就了一种糟糕的编程语言呢？
I just want to spend this video talking about these three questions. And as we'll see, I
我只想用这段视频来谈谈这三个问题。正如我们将看到的，我
think the answers to these questions are largely independent of the technical aspects of language
我认为这些问题的答案在很大程度上独立于语言的技术方面
design and implementation. But very interesting in their own right.
设计和实施。但它们本身就很有趣。
So let's begin with the question of why there are so many programming languages. And at
那么，让我们从为什么会有这么多编程语言的问题开始。以及在
least a partial answer to this question is not too hard to come by. If you think for
至少这个问题的部分答案并不太难得到。如果你认为
a few minutes, you'd realize that the application domains for programming have very distinctive
几分钟后，您就会意识到用于编程的应用程序域具有非常独特的
and conflicting needs. That is, it's very hard to design one language that would actually
和相互冲突的需求。也就是说，很难设计出一种能够真正
do everything in every situation for all programmers.
在任何情况下为所有程序员做任何事情。
And let's just go through some examples. One domain that you might not think about very
让我们来看看一些例子。一个您可能不太会考虑的领域
much is scientific computing. So these are all the big calculations that are done for
很多都是科学计算。这些就是我们要做的所有大计算
engineering applications primarily but also big science and long running experiments,
主要是工程应用，但也有大科学和长期运行的实验，
simulation experiments.
仿真实验。
And what are the needs for such computations? Well typically you need very good floating
这样的计算又有什么需要呢？嗯，通常情况下，你需要非常好的漂浮力
point support. I'll abbreviate that as FP. You need good support for arrays and operations
点支撑点。我把它缩写为FP。您需要对阵列和操作提供良好的支持
on arrays because the most common data type in most scientific applications is larger
在阵列上，因为大多数科学应用程序中最常见的数据类型是较大的
arrays of floating point numbers. And then you also need parallelism.
浮点数的数组。然后你还需要并行性。
Today to get sufficient
今天就能得到足够的
performance you really have to exploit parallelism in these applications.
性能您确实必须在这些应用程序中利用并行性。
And it's not every language actually supports all of these things well. This is actually
并不是每种语言都能很好地支持所有这些东西。这实际上是
not an exhaustive list of the things you need but a few distinctive things that are needed.
不是你所需要的东西的详尽清单，而是一些你需要的有特色的东西。
But one language that has traditionally done a very good job of supporting these things
但是有一种语言传统上在支持这些东西方面做得非常好
is Fortran. And Fortran is still heavily used in the scientific community.
是Fortran。而Fortran仍然在科学界大量使用。
It was originally designed for scientific applications. If you recall that the name
它最初是为科学应用而设计的。如果你还记得那个名字
means formula translation. And it has evolved over time. It doesn't really look much like
意思是公式翻译。而且它是随着时间的推移而演变的。它看起来真的不太像
the original language anymore but it's always retain this core constituency in scientific
原来的语言已经不存在了，但它始终保留着这一核心的科学基础
computing and remains one of the leading languages in that domain.
并且仍然是该领域的领先语言之一。
Now a completely different kind of a domain is business applications. And so what do you
现在，一个完全不同类型的领域是业务应用程序。那么你是怎么做的呢？
need here? Well so here you're going to need things like persistence. You don't want to
需要在这里吗？那么，在这里，你需要一些东西，比如坚持不懈。你不会想要的
lose your data. Businesses go to a lot of trouble to get the data, and they need a way
丢失您的数据。企业不厌其烦地获取数据，他们需要一种方法
to hold onto it, and they want that to be extremely reliable.
来保住它，他们希望它是极其可靠的。
You're going to need good report facilities. Because typically you want to do something
你需要好的报告设备。因为通常你会想要做一些
with the data. So you need good facilities for report generation. And also, you want
有了这些数据。因此，您需要良好的工具来生成报告。还有，你想要
to be able to exploit the data. The data's actually in many modern businesses one of
才能利用这些数据。这些数据实际上在许多现代企业中都是
the most valuable assets and so you need good facilities for asking questions about your
最有价值的资产，因此您需要良好的设施来询问有关您的
data. Let's call it data analysis.
数据。让我们称其为数据分析。
And again, this is not an exhaustive list of things that you need, but it is representative
再说一次，这不是您需要的全部清单，但它具有代表性
I would say. And probably the most common or one of the most common used languages for
我会说。可能是最常用或最常用的语言之一
this class of applications is SQL, the database query language. So relational databases and
这类应用程序是SQL，即数据库查询语言。所以关系数据库和
their associated programming language-- languages, I should say, but most notably SQL-- really
他们的相关编程语言--语言，我应该说，但最引人注目的是SQL--真的
dominate in this application domain.
在此应用程序域中占据主导地位。
And then another domain, let's do one more, is systems programming.
然后另一个领域，让我们再做一个，是系统编程。
So by this I mean things like embedded systems, things to control devices, operating systems, things like that.
所以我这里指的是嵌入式系统，控制设备的东西，操作系统，诸如此类的东西。
And what are the characteristics here? Well, we need very low level control of the resources.
这里有什么特色呢？嗯，我们需要对资源进行非常低级别的控制。
The whole point of systems programming is to do a good job of managing resources and
系统编程的重点是做好资源的管理和管理
so we really want fine grained control over the resources. And often there's a time aspect,
所以我们真的想要对资源进行细粒度的控制。通常情况下会有时间方面的问题，
so you might have some real time constraints. So you need to be able to reason about time.
所以你可能会有一些实时的时间限制。所以你需要能够对时间进行推理。
Because these are actually again devices and they need to be able to react within certain
因为这些实际上又是设备，它们需要能够在特定的时间内做出反应
amount of time - if it's a network device or something like that - you need to be responsive
时间长短-如果是网络设备或类似设备-您需要响应
to the network. Lots and lots of examples where timing is important. And these are just
连接到网络。很多很多的例子表明时机很重要。而这些只是
two aspects and I'm a little bit - I'm running out of space here so I'll just stop with that.
有两个方面，我有一点-我的空间快用完了，所以我就到此为止了。
But again these are representative of the kinds of things you need in systems programming.
但是，这些也代表了您在系统编程中需要的东西。
And probably today still the most widely used systems programming language or family systems
今天可能仍然是使用最广泛的系统编程语言或家庭系统
of programming languages is the C and to some extent C++ family of languages.
编程语言中最重要的是C语言，在某种程度上，还有C++语言系列。
And as you can see the requirements in these different domains are just completely
正如您所看到的，这些不同领域中的需求完全是
different from each other. What's important in one domain or most important in one
彼此不同。在一个领域中什么是重要的，或者在一个领域中最重要的是什么
domain is not the same as in another domain. And it's easy I think to imagine at least
域与另一个域中的域不同。我想这很容易想象至少
that it would be difficult to integrate all of these into one system that would do a good
很难将所有这些集成到一个系统中，这样做会很好
job on all of these things.
所有这些东西的工作。
That brings us to our second question: Why are there new programming languages?
这就引出了我们的第二个问题：为什么会有新的编程语言？
There are so many languages in existence, why would we ever need to design a new one? And I'm
现有的语言如此之多，我们为什么还要设计一种新的语言呢？而且我是
going to begin the answer to this question with an observation that at first glance has
我将以一个乍一看的观察来开始回答这个问题
nothing to do with the question at all. So let me just take a moment to explain it.
跟这个问题一点关系都没有。所以让我花点时间来解释一下。
I claim that programmer training is the dominant cost for a programming language. And I think
我认为程序员培训是编程语言的主要成本。我认为
this is really important so just going to emphasize the bit that's important here. It's
这真的很重要，所以我只想强调一下这里的重要部分。它是
the programmer training. The cost of educating the programmers in the language. So we think
程序员培训。用这种语言教育程序员的成本。所以我们认为
about a programming language there are several things that have to happen for that language
关于一种编程语言，该语言必须发生几件事
to get used. Somebody has to design it. But that's really not very expensive. That's just
才能习惯。总得有人来设计它。但是那真的不是很贵。那只是
one or very few people typically. Somebody has to build a compiler, but that is also
通常是一个人或很少的人。必须有人构建一个编译器，但这也是
not actually all that expensive. Maybe 10 to 20 people for a really large compiler project
其实没那么贵。一个非常大的编译器项目可能需要10到20个人
can build quite a good compiler.
可以构建一个相当不错的编译器。
The real cost is in all the users and educating them. So if you have thousands or hundreds
真正的成本在于所有的用户和教育他们。所以如果你有几千或上百个
of thousands or millions of users of the language, the time and money that it takes to teach
对于成千上万或数百万的语言使用者来说，教授这门语言所需的时间和金钱
them all the language is really the dominant cost. And here I don't mean just the actual
他们所有的语言确实是占主导地位的成本。这里我指的不仅仅是实际的
dollar expense of buying textbooks and taking classes and things like that.
买课本、上课之类的美元开销。
It's also the fact that the programmers have to decide it's worth it for them to learn
还有一个事实是，程序员必须决定他们是否值得学习
this language and many programmers learn on their own time, but that's a use of their
这门语言和许多程序员都是在自己的时间里学习的，但这是对他们的
time and the expense of their time is a real economic cost. And so if you think about the
时间和时间的花费是一种真正的经济成本。所以如果你想一想
number of hours that it takes to teach a population of a million programmers a language, that's
教给一百万程序员一门语言所需的小时数，也就是
really quite a significant economic investment.
确实是一项相当可观的经济投资。
Now from this observation, we can make a couple of predictions pretty easily. And again, these
现在从这个观察中，我们可以很容易地做出几个预测。再说一遍，这些
are just predictions now that follow from this claim. If you believe that it's true.
现在只是根据这一说法做出的预测。如果你相信这是真的。
So let me erase it and fix it. So first prediction is that widely used languages will be slow
所以让我把它擦掉然后修好。所以第一个预测是广泛使用的语言将会很慢
to change. And why should that be true? Well, if I make a change to a language of lots of
去改变。为什么会这样呢？嗯，如果我改变了一种有很多语言的语言
people use, I have to educate everybody in that community about the change. And so even
人们使用，我必须教育那个社区的每个人关于这一变化。所以即使是这样
relatively minor language extensions small changes to syntax, small new features, even
相对较小的语言扩展语法的小更改、小的新功能，甚至
just simple changes in the interface of the compiler, if you have a lot of users it takes
只需对编译器的界面进行简单的更改，如果您有很多用户，则需要
a very long time and is quite expensive to teach them all about that.
这需要很长的时间，而且教给他们所有这方面的知识是相当昂贵的。
So as languages become widely used the rate of change, their rate of change will slow
因此，随着语言的广泛使用，它们的变化速度将会减慢
down. And this predicts over time as the world of programming grows, as we have more more
放下。这预示着随着时间的推移，随着编程世界的发展，我们拥有更多
programmers in the world, we would expect the most popular languages, which will have
世界上的程序员，我们期待着最流行的语言，这将有
larger and larger user bases so larger and larger programmer basis, to become more and
越来越大的用户群，所以越来越多的程序员基础，以变得越来越多
more ossified. To evolve more and more slowly. And I think actually what you see in practice
更僵化了。进化得越来越慢。我认为实际上你在实践中看到的
is very consistent with that prediction.
与这一预测非常一致。
Now at the other end of the spectrum, this same observation makes an almost what appears
现在，在光谱的另一端，同样的观察得出了几乎看起来像是
to be contradictory prediction, which is that easy to start, it's easy to start a new language.
矛盾的预测，这是那么容易开始，它很容易开始一门新的语言。
That in fact the cost of starting up a new language is very low. And why is that? Well
事实上，开始一门新语言的成本非常低。为什么会这样呢？井
because you start with zero users and so there is essentially zero training cost at the beginning
因为您从零用户开始，因此从一开始就基本上没有培训成本
and then even when you have just a few users the cost of teaching them the changes in the
然后，即使您只有几个用户，教他们了解
language is not very high. And it's so new languages can evolve much more quickly. They
语言不是很高。因此，新的语言可以发展得更快。他们
can adapt much more quickly to changing situations. And it's just not very costly to experiment
可以更快地适应不断变化的情况。而且实验成本并不是很高
with a new language at all. And there's a tension between these two things.
学习一门新的语言。这两件事之间有一种张力。
When is a programmer going to choose between a widely used existing language that perhaps
程序员什么时候会在一种广泛使用的现有语言之间做出选择，也许
doesn't change very quickly, and a brand new language? Well they're going to choose it
变化不是很快，而一种全新的语言呢？嗯，他们会选择它的
if the productivity, if their productivity exceeds the training cost. So if they perceive
如果生产力，如果他们的生产力超过了培训成本。所以如果他们察觉到
that by spending a little bit of time and money to learn this new language, they're
通过花费一点时间和金钱来学习这门新语言，他们
going to be much more productive over a relatively short period of time then they're going to
在相对较短的时间内，他们的工作效率会大大提高
make the switch.
进行切换。
So when is this likely to happen? Well putting this all together languages are most likely
那么，这可能会在什么时候发生呢？嗯，把所有这些放在一起，语言是最有可能的
to be adopted  to fill a void. And again this is a prediction that follows from the fact that programmer
被采用来填补一个空白。再说一次，这是一种预测，它是基于这样一个事实，即程序员
training is the main cost. What do I mean by this? Well what I mean is that, programming
培训是主要成本。我这么说是什么意思？我的意思是，编程
languages exist for purpose, people use them to get work done. And because we're still
语言的存在是有目的的，人们用它们来完成工作。因为我们还在
in the middle of the information revolution and there are new application domains coming
在信息革命的中期，新的应用领域不断涌现
along all the time.
一直都是这样。
So there are new kinds of programming that emerge every few years or even more often
所以每隔几年甚至更频繁就会出现一些新的编程方式
than that. So just in terms of recent history mobile applications are now something that's
比那还多。因此，就最近的历史而言，移动应用程序现在是
relatively new. And there's a lot of new technology being built up to support mobile computing.
相对较新。有许多新技术正在建立起来，以支持移动计算。
A few years ago it was the internet itself was a new programming platform and a bunch
几年前，互联网本身就是一个新的编程平台
of new programming languages like Java in particular got started during that time.
特别是Java等新的编程语言在此期间开始使用。
So a new programming niche is open up because the technology changes that what people want
因此，一个新的编程利基市场打开了，因为技术改变了人们想要的
to do with software changes. And this creates new opportunities for languages. The old languages
与软件变更有关。这为语言创造了新的机会。古老的语言
are slow to change and so they have some difficulty in adapting to fit these new domains. And
变化很慢，所以他们在适应这些新领域方面有一些困难。和
they aren't really necessarily well suited to them for the reasons we talked about on
由于我们前面谈到的原因，它们不一定真的很适合它们
the previous slide with the previous question because it's hard to have one language that
上一张幻灯片和上一个问题，因为很难有一种语言
incorporates all the features you would want.
集成了您想要的所有功能。
And so there are so these languages are not necessarily perfect for these application
因此，这些语言对于这些应用程序来说不一定是完美的
domains. They're slow to adapt to the new situation. And this tends to call forth new
域。他们适应新形势的速度很慢。而这往往会带来新的
languages. So when there's a new opportunity and some application domain. If there are
语言。因此，当有新的机会和某个应用领域时。如果有
enough programmers to support the language, often a new language will arise.
有足够的程序员来支持这种语言，往往会出现一种新的语言。
Just want to point out another prediction that can be made from this one observation.
我只想指出从这一观察中可以做出的另一个预测。
That programmer training and I'll underline that, is a dominant cost per programming language.
我要强调的是，程序员培训是每种编程语言的主要成本。
And that is that new languages  tend to look like old languages. That is that new languages are rarely if ever completely
这就是说，新的语言往往看起来像旧的语言。这就是说，新语言很少(如果有的话)是完全
new. They have a family resemblance to some predecessor language sometimes a number of
新的。它们与一些以前的语言有家族相似之处，有时有许多
predecessor languages.
前置语言。
And why is that? Well partly that it's hard to think of truly new things. But also I think
为什么会这样呢？嗯，部分原因是很难想出真正新鲜的东西。但我也认为
if there's an economic benefit to this namely that it reduces the training cost by having
如果这样做有经济效益，即通过以下方式降低培训成本
your new language look like an old language, by leveraging off what people already know
通过利用人们已经知道的东西，你的新语言看起来像是一种旧语言
about the old language, you make it easier for people to learn the language and make
关于古老的语言，你让人们更容易学习这种语言，并使
them learn it more quickly. And the most classic example of this is a Java versus C++, where
他们学得更快。最经典的例子是Java与C++，其中
Java was designed to look a lot like C++. And that was I think very conscious to make
Java的设计看起来很像C++。我认为这是非常有意识的
it easy for all of the existing C++ programmers to start programming in Java.
对于所有现有的C++程序员来说，开始使用Java编程都很容易。
Finally, we can ask ourselves what is a good programming language. And here unfortunately
最后，我们可以问问自己什么是好的编程语言。不幸的是，在这里
the situation is much less clear. I would just make one claim that there is no and I'll
情况就不那么明朗了。我只想声明一件事，那就是没有，我会
emphasize no universally accepted metric for language design. And what I mean by that?
强调语言设计没有普遍接受的衡量标准。我这么说是什么意思？
Well I guess the most important part of this statement is the universally accepted bit.
嗯，我想这个声明中最重要的部分是普遍接受的比特。
So I mean that people don't agree on what makes a good language.
所以我的意思是，人们对什么才是一门好的语言意见不一。
There are lots of metrics out there and people have proposed lots of ways of measuring programming
现在有很多度量标准，人们提出了很多衡量编程的方法
languages but most people don't believe that these are very good measures and there is
语言，但大多数人不认为这些是很好的措施，而且有
certainly no consensus. If you just look at the world of programmers, they can't agree
当然没有达成共识。如果你只看程序员的世界，他们不会同意
on what the best language is and to convince yourself of this, just go and take a look
关于什么是最好的语言，要让自己相信这一点，只要去看看就行了
at any of the many news group posts where people get into a semi religious arguments
在许多新闻组的帖子中，任何一个都会让人们陷入半宗教的争论
about why one group of languages or particular language is better than another language.
关于为什么一组语言或特定语言比另一种语言更好。
But even in the research community in the scientific community in among people who design
但即使是在科学界的研究界，在设计
languages, I would say there is no universally accepted consensus on what makes a good language.
关于语言，我想说，关于什么是好的语言，没有一个普遍接受的共识。
And to just kind of illustrate the difficulties in trying to come up with such a metric, let
为了说明尝试提出这样一个度量的困难，让我们
me discuss one that I've heard people propose in all seriousness and that is that a good
我要讨论的是我听到人们非常认真地提出的一个建议，那就是一个很好的
language  is one people use. And let me put a question mark on that because I don't believe this
语言是人们使用的一种语言。让我在上面打个问号，因为我不相信
statement.
声明。
And I think a moment's reflection with a moment's reflection I can convince you that this isn't
我认为片刻的反省加上片刻的反省我可以说服你这不是
a great measure. On the positive side I guess the argument for this is that it's a very
这是一个很大的衡量标准。从积极的一面来看，我猜这个的论点是，这是一个非常
clear measure. It measures the popularity of the language. How many people are actually
明确衡量标准。它衡量的是这种语言的受欢迎程度。实际上有多少人
using it and presumably languages are more widely used for a good reason. In some sense
使用它，想必语言被更广泛地使用是有很好的理由的。在某种意义上说
perhaps they are better languages. But this would imply if you believe this and follow
也许它们是更好的语言。但这意味着如果你相信这一点并遵循
it its logical conclusion that Visual Basic is the best language above all other programming
Visual Basic是最好的编程语言，这是合乎逻辑的结论
languages.
语言。
And I've nothing against Visual Basic. It's a well designed system but I don't even think
而且我也不反对Visual Basic。这是一个设计得很好的系统，但我甚至不认为
the designers of Visual Basic, would claim that it is in fact the world's best programming
Visual Basic的设计者会声称它实际上是世界上最好的编程
language. And as we saw in the discussion that we just had, there are many, many other
语言。正如我们在刚才的讨论中看到的，还有很多很多其他的
factors besides technical excellence that go into whether a programming languages is
除了技术卓越之外，编程语言是否
widely used or not.
不管是否被广泛使用。
And in fact technical excellence is probably not even the most important reason that a
事实上，卓越的技术可能甚至不是最重要的原因
language might be used. It has much more to do with whether it addresses a niche or application
可能会使用语言。它与它是否针对某个利基市场或应用程序有更多关系
domain for which there isn't a better tool. And then once it's established and has lots
没有更好的工具的领域。一旦它建立起来，并且有很多
of users of course there's inertia in history that aided in surviving. And that's why we
当然，用户也有历史上的惰性，帮助他们生存下来。这就是为什么我们
still have Fortran and Cobalt and lots of other languages from long long ago that we
还有Fortran、Cobalt和许多很久以前的其他语言，我们
could if we were starting over today designed much better.
如果我们今天重新开始的话会设计得更好。
So to conclude this video on the economy of programming languages, I think the two most
所以总结这段关于编程语言经济性的视频，我认为两个最重要的
important things to remember are that application domains have conflicting needs and therefore
需要记住的重要一点是，应用程序域具有相互冲突的需求，因此
it is difficult to design one system that incorporates everything that you would like
很难设计出一个包含您想要的一切的系统。
to have. So you can't get all the features that you would like into a single system in
才能拥有。因此，您不能将您想要的所有功能都放入单个系统中
a coherent design at least it's very hard to do that and so it takes a lot of time to
一个连贯的设计，至少很难做到这一点，所以要花很多时间
add new features to existing systems.
向现有系统添加新功能。
And the second point is that programmer training is the dominant cost for programming
第二点是程序员培训是编程的主要成本
language. And together these two things, these two observations, these really explain why
语言。把这两件事，这两个观察放在一起，这就解释了为什么
we get new programming languages, because the old languages are difficult to change
我们得到了新的编程语言，因为旧的语言很难改变
and when we have new opportunities, it's often easier and more direct to just design a new
当我们有新的机会时，通常更容易和更直接地设计一个新的
language for those rather than trying to move the entire community of programmers and an
语言，而不是试图推动整个程序员社区和
existing systems to accommodate those new applications.
现有的系统来适应这些新的应用程序。